Nicolás Urdaneta

Phone: (+57) 3212455640

n.urdaneta@uniandes.edu.co

Profile

I am a research assistant at the Economics Faculty at Universidad de Los Andes, Colombia, working for Marcela Eslava on firm dynamics, productivity, and market power. I hold a M.A and a B.A. in economics from Universidad de Los Andes. I am primarily interested in approaching problems through empirical work with structural models. My current interests in research are towards firm dynamics, innovation, trade, economic development, and applied econometrics. I have also worked on other topics in independent projects that include internal migration and displacement in Colombia and gender bias in student evaluations of teaching.

EDUCATION

2019 - 2021	M.A. Economics, cum laude, Universidad de los Andes - Bogotá, Colombia
2015 - 2019	B.A. Economics, <i>cum laude</i> , Universidad de los Andes - Bogotá, Colombia

Research Experience

Jun. 2019 -	Research Assistant for Marcela Eslava, Full-Professor and Economics Faculty		
Present	Dean, Universidad de Los Andes. Main research projects joint with John Haltiwanger and Marcela Meléndez.		
Dec. 2019 - Feb. 2020	Data research assistant for Adriana Corredor-Waldron, Postdoctoral Research Associate, Princeton University.		

Working papers

The Size and Life-Cycle Growth of Plants: The Role of Productivity, Demand, and Wedges. With Marcela Eslava and John Haltiwanger.

Market Concentration, Market Fragmentation, and Inequality in Latin America. (2021). UNDP LAC Working Paper No. 11. Background Paper for the UNDP LAC Regional Human Development Report 2021. With *Marcela Eslava and Marcela Meléndez*. Document available here.

"Talented" Men and "Kind" Women? Gender Bias in Student Evaluations of Teaching. (2021). Documento CEDE No. 46. (Master's thesis). Document available here. In the media: El Espectador.

Work in progress

Equilibrium Gender Discrimination in Student Evaluation of Teaching. With Sara Ayllon, Lars Lefgren, Richard Patterson, and Olga Stoddard.

Reconciling the Effects of Migration: Do the Opportunity Costs Shape the Local Effects?. With Mateo Arbeláez and Juan Sebastián Muñoz.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Graduate Teacher Assistant - Universidad de Los Andes				
2020 II	Impact Evaluation for Public Policy (prof. Adriana Camacho)			
2020 Summer	Intermediate Econometrics (prof. Mateo Arbeláez)			
2020 I	World Economic History (prof. Leopoldo Fergusson and Juan Sebastián Galán)			
2019 II-2020 I	Intermediate Macroeconomics (prof. David Pérez and Andrés Zambrano)			

Undergraduate Teacher Assistant - Universidad de Los Andes

2018 II - 2019 I Monetary Policy and Theory 2018 Summer Intermediate Econometrics 2017 Summer Intermediate Microeconomics

2017 II Mathematical Methods for Economics

2017 I Pentagon. Study hall for Calculus 3, integral Calculus, Linear Algebra, and

Differential Calculus.

2016 II Integral Calculus

AWARDS

2011	Sixth place National Colombian Mathematical Olympics 30th Edition. First
	level category.
2019	One of the best results in the Colombian higher education examinations
	(Saber-Pro). The award was given to 1,324 graduates out of over 240,000.
2019	Placed in the top 3% of the previous 5 years of graduates in the B.A. in
	economics, Los Andes University (cum laude).
2021	Placed in the top 3% of the previous 5 years of graduates in the M.A. in
	economics, Los Andes University (cum laude).

OTHER EXPERIENCE

Supuestos Economics Magazine (2016 - 2019). This is the economics student's magazine from Universidad de Los Andes. I held multiple roles: Editorial Director (2019), Revision and Edition Sub Director (2018), Communications Sub Director (2017 II). Six publications in printed edition, including two main articles. Link to website (in Spanish).

SKILLS

Stata, R & Latex	Advanced	Python & Julia	Basic		
Languages					
English	Fluent	Spanish	Native Language		
REFERENCES					
Marcela Eslava	Full Professor and Economics Faculty Dean, Universidad de Los Andes. meslava@uniandes.edu.co				
John Haltiwanger	Distinguished University Professor, University of Maryland. halt@umd.edu				
Adriana Camacho	Associate Professor,	Universidad de Los Andes. a	dcamach@uniandes.edu.co		
Lars Lefgren	Department Chair lars_lefgren@byu.edu	, 0	nam Young University.		